is quite straightforward
no you don't need to believe in rebirth
but you also
need to not disbelieve in it either
usually people think oh
i need some sort of proof in order to
believe in rebirth
and you won't find it you can't prove
you can't provide a proof of the senses
the scientific proof of the sense
objects and measurements and
and so on that cannot prove that which
is beyond the senses which is after them
so
if you're looking for a type of proof
uh for the next life you won't find one
but the point is
uh if you also look for a proof that
there is no next life you won't find one
either so what you need to recognize is that
so what you need to recognize is that
that is pretty much your situation
you're not in a position to know what do
you do then that's the really
because it's uh you know the question of
next life what's you know
what's after death it's not something
you can be um
indifferent to words i mean
choosing to be indifferent towards it
it's already basically choosing a belief
that there is nothing after the after
this life so see
fundamentally you're gonna start acting on the basis
you're gonna start acting on the basis
of one belief or the other
because it is equally fundamentally
something that does concern every human
existence you know what is after this
what is after these senses that i'm so
familiar with what is after this world
what is after this
this mind this sense of self and so on
so so what do you do then
like um
you can't find the proof that there is
next life you can't find a proof that
there is in the next life
so
you don't actually need proof we need to
recognize that's exactly a starting
position that you should never abandon
you are not in a position to know
yet it concerns you deep down it affects
your life
um it affects your attitude towards this
life you know
like basically the attitude towards
what's after does affect the attitude
you have towards this life and that's
the point that you should start uh
reflecting on
and that's what it would encourage those
people that
kind of there is you can't know there
isn't but you should ask yourself okay
so in case that there is
those people who say that there is
they kind of say that it does matter
what you do in this life you know and
then next life
you'll be rewarded or you'll be punished
in you know in the simplest terms so you
just what if that's what what did that
that is the case what if that's the
truth so you don't know you can't prove
you can't prove it you can't disprove it
so let's assume then for myself
that that's correct what do i have to do
what am i asked to do
by those people who say oh after this
life yeah there is something and if you
behave well that comes if you don't
behave well something else will come of
of a bad you know
punishment form
so so like in the buddhist teaching at
least what you're required to do is
be virtuous be generous be kind not act
out of anger last practice sense
restraint so if you stop and think about
it
those are good things in this life as
well so if there is a next life you'll be
so if there is a next life you'll be
rewarded for that behavior if there
isn't a next life what you're rewarded
in this life
because as i said
everybody values that doesn't matter how
careless how unrestrained people are
they still value
honesty deep down they still value a
person of integrity they still value a
person with a set of values that you
know that they have upon uh upon the
life so
so you will benefit from that
and um and in case that there isn't a
next life that's fine but at least you
win in this life so
basically acting under the assumption in the worst
acting under the assumption in the worst
case scenario that there is a next life
and if i don't behave i'll be punished
if you assume that to be your belief
doesn't matter even if it's like as
rational as this it will be beneficial
for you
because uh that as i said doesn't matter
how much
how how how far he moved the this type
of kind of belief might be deep down it
does affect your attitude towards this
life as i said if you choose to not
think about it you're just to be
indifferent what's after that is already
you're directing your belief that will
affect what type of actions and
responsibility you you have in this life
and whether you take it or not
so if you consciously make the effort to
contemplate what is after in that sense
and then assume not like try to figure
out what's after i don't mean that i
mean more like in case that there is
after it's good to behave in this life plus
it's good to behave in this life plus
i'll be rewarded in this life for the
good behavior um and i will be um
more free from hassle harassment you
know if i'm not immortal cheating
stealing and thomas or keeping the
precepts so it's a win-win either way
it's a win-win
if you choose to dismiss what's after
again even if you're a good person deep
down that will affect your choices in
terms of avoiding responsibility valuing
the current pleasure of the senses and
so on
so it's not as good and then
if there is actually the the next life
the way people say there is and you
haven't been behaving properly
uh you haven't practiced sufficient
amount of sensory strength you'll be too
dependent on the senses and sensuality
and carelessness and so on then you pay
the price there as well so so you lose
um
so so that's why practically speaking
it's actually better to assume that
there is
not out of a conviction oh i know there
is because i believe in the buddha or
something just out of pure practical reasoning so
just out of pure practical reasoning so
that it will influence your decisions
you make in this life
and uh
and that brings me to the point of that
sense restraint and sensuality because
you know even in christianity um there
were some some thinkers they were kind
of suggesting the similar saying you
should accept that there is a heaven
even if you don't know
because the reward of it will be great
and uh and it will you know nothing can
match it
uh and in case that there isn't heaven
it doesn't matter you know it's good to
believe that there is but those thinkers
and in particular that whole famous
philosophy pascal's wager
because some people will confuse this
what the buddha instructed with pascal's
wager but the fundamental difference
there is pascal did not see the benefit
of abandoning or restraining sensuality
in this life the buddha did
and so it's not a pascal's wager that
which were the teachers
pascal he thought himself that giving up
desires of the flesh and senses in this
life or at least restraining them is a loss
or at least restraining them is a loss
is a factual loss but he tried to argue
by saying well that factual loss of
restraining yourself and not pursuing
the pleasure of the senses visible here
and now
it's worth kind of a risk because if
there is a great reward of heaven it
will be worth it but that's not really a
sound logical argument because well what
if there isn't and you lose twice but
actually the buddha doesn't say that he
says that sense restraint in this life
is good even if there is no next life
because well ask yourself again
what is the state of mind of of us of
sensuality and sense of desire it's a
pressure it's an addiction it's pleasant
when you can satisfy it
it's unpleasant when you can't satisfy
it
either way you're under the pressure of
that thing so wouldn't we wouldn't it be
better even in this life
if for example you would not be as
pressured let's say you're not able you
don't have to go away and give it all up
but say if you're able to practice sense
restraint wouldn't that result in
increased amount of patience
tolerance virtue imperfectability
virtue imperfectability
or good values useful for other areas of
this life as well
alternatively if you always scratch your
edge when it itches you know like a like
a wild dog
what would that result in
would that be a calming sort of you know
practice that would result in further
calmness of the mind
or would that result in further
aggravating of the issue and the
pressure you're under when you
experience desire
addiction think of an addict as we said
before fundamentally there's a great pleasure
fundamentally there's a great pleasure
of you know injecting
caring or a substance you're dependent
on
but overall the context of being a
serious addict whose life depends on
that substance it's actually very
unwholesome and you know that so if you
if your mind is controlled by the sense
desires the more you give into it the
more the control they will exercise over
you so sense restraint is good in this life
so sense restraint is good in this life
even if there is no future reward for it
plus if there is a future reward you win
win again so thus this is very different
and very far and much more profound than
anything pascal could have thought of so
the whole point here is to
to use these reflections to influence
your decisions in this life sense
restraint and as i said you don't have
to you know think oh so i must become a
man can be celibate sure if you want to
go all the way that's fine
but actually even practicing
uh mere sense restraint in terms of the
five precepts has the benefit here and
now visible to you if you do it
and like as i said this various phenomena
like as i said this various phenomena
like patience for example it's useful to
have it
wouldn't be useful
to to you know
be under the pressure desire to get
something but not be moved by it
uh to the extent that you suffer so you
patiently wait
and sometimes wouldn't that also
increase the further context of your
life such as well if i actually wait now
i might gain more late you know business
investments and so on
but that needs to be developed patience
does not come out of impulsive
scratching of the age patience comes
exactly on account of sense restraint on
a kind of abstaining the immediate
gratification and satisfaction of you
know ideas thoughts desires and so on so
even in this life there will be direct
benefits of sense restraint
and if there is a next life there will
be even further benefits of that same
sensory strategy in this life on account
of which you already benefited so it's
it's a it's actually a great thing it's
a good thing because it's a win-win as
the buddha said in that suture